Hi and welcome back to Living in Central
Texas. I'm Andrea Dudik, real estate
broker and relocation specialist here in
the Central Texas area. If you are
considering relocating to the area and
are eyeing the areas of Temple, Belton,
or Celo, you'll definitely want to watch
this video. I'm going to give you a
brief overview of each of those areas,
some of the most developing and um best
communities happening in those places,
highlighting some of the builders that
are building there, as well as uh what
incentives and our current market is
looking like. So, I'm really excited
about this video. I can't wait to go
over these things with you. And if you
are interested in more things relocation
related to the area, don't forget to
subscribe to my channel um or even
download my free relocation guide to
help get you started. All right, so
let's dive on in. We will be using Loom
to kind of screen share with me, look at
the MLS, get a really good map idea of
inventory in our little triangle of
Temple Belt and it's going to be a lot
of fun.
[Music]
Okay, so let's head on into the MLS.
This is what I would use to kickstart
your home search. Of course, I have
really great knowledge of different
builders in these areas. Um, I'm
frequently getting inventory from each
of these builders, finding out what
incentives are. So, if we find little
things in here, um, I will always reach
out to the builders and see what their
most upto-date inventory is, as well as
kind of dive into what incentives and
concessions are being offered. All
right. So, today we're going to be
looking at active listings in Temple,
Belton, and File. We're actually going
to look at 2024 or newer because since
there is such a surplus of inventory,
even though we are in 2025, there's
still a lot of new construction homes in
that 2025 2024 age range. So, within
Temple, Belt, and Toledo, new
construction homes, 2024 or newer, we
have 340 listings. What we're going to
do is look at the map here and talk a
little bit about each of these areas. We
zoom in a tiny bit. Got the temple area,
Belton, the Leato down here. So, let's
take a look at the map here just to give
us a really great idea of what's
available. So, looking at this map,
there's going to be some overlap,
especially with Temple and Belton.
Things are a little bit different.
Again, I think there are a lot more
homes technically in Temple, but what I
find is that my buyers are more
interested if they've got kids or
something in the school district, if
anything, because there's such overlap.
You can have a Temple address, but be
within Belton ISD. You can be in Temple
and part of Temple ISD. So, if we're
working together, that's one of the
things I'll check with Temple Belton,
which of course includes Morgan's Point.
I have an awesome video on Morgan's
Point if you want to check that out. and
then Celo down here. A lot of houses,
you can see a lot of these are near
Belton Lake. This is Stillhouse Lake.
So, let's start with Temple. Temple is
going to be really great proximity to
hospitals. We have MLAN Children's
Hospital, Baylor Scott and White Main
Hospital. We're a huge medical hub here
and you're just going to have some
really great both new and established
neighborhoods. Great access to shopping.
And then you're right on the I35
corridor. If we back up here, the I35
runs down here. So, smack through Cedo,
Temple, and Belton. So, in terms of
investment, this area is growing
rapidly. It's a great place to invest
and buy in my opinion. If you go north,
we have Waco. If you go south, we have
Austin. Closer you get to Waco, slightly
higher price per square foot. Definitely
closer to Austin, a higher price per
square foot. Theo is generally going to
be higher price points, higher price per
square foot, but you're also going to
get rural and private feel, generally
larger lot. And then if you're looking
for more kind of historic charm,
lakeside lifestyle, and then just quick
access to Fort Cavazos, 14 is going to
take you out to Fort Cavazos right here.
Temple, Belin, you really can't go
wrong. Everything's really close to one
another. It's just a matter of what
you're looking for. And then you have
more artistic upscale golf community
lifestyle boutique feel. A lot of custom
homes, larger lots. I mean, people are
really just driving around on the their
golf carts drinking beer on a Sunday a
lot of times. Different feels, different
price points. So again, price per square
foot is going to be a little higher in.
We'll see that as we look at these
homes. So let's go. Of those 350 plus
homes that we saw, 234 of them are in
Temple. These are all temple homes. I'm
going to sort by price. You have a one
bed, one bath here at 149. Kind of a
downtown area. Some of our newer
communities, we have Adoscosa Estates
over $300,000 price point. 300,000 is
our average home priceish 280 to 300 in
the moment. And if we look at the map,
Atcosa Estates is 363 and 35. really
great access whether you're going up 35.
It's just our big circle that takes us
everywhere. So in here in this community
we have builders in Atcosa Estates. We
have Berry Wright Homes, Cory Herring,
Fentex Homes. This is Dunhill Homes. A
lot of different builders to pick from
here. Just over that 300,000 price
point. 1,600 square ft². This one's
three bed, two bath, brand new. Tons of
inventory. Our lot sizes
are.17ish.20 or a fifth of an acre. Very
small lot. A couple more really popular
communities are Hartrick Ranch. I just
did a video on that one. Really awesome
community out near Little River Academy
on the outskirts. I think this area is
growing very quickly and has so much
potential. This one's actually Academy
ISD which is pretty soughta. Some really
beautiful builders out here. We have
Stylecraft Omega and Gila Hartrick
Ranch. Again, this is 35. Here we have
Celo. You have 14 running through
Belton. This is off of
FM93, which is right here. Super rural,
really cute little area. Really
beautiful homes and builders. So, what
I'm seeing here currently in our market,
which this is always subject to change
in this community specifically, able to
get a large amount of closing costs. I
think on the last deal, like over
$20,000 in concessions, which is like
money that can be used in various ways.
My client was able to buy down their
permanent fixed interest rate to far
below the average market value, all
their closing costs paid for, and we got
them a garage door opener because
motorized garage door opener is not
included. Something you don't always
think of. Just depending on where you're
looking to go, we can figure out what we
can negotiate for you. Homes in there
pretty similar, closer to the 300 and
just over $300,000 price point. Similar
size lots, actually slightly smaller
lots, but I'm going to show you one of
them. And let's see if I can show you
one that's finished just so you can see
the inside of them. Okay, this is a Kila
build priced at 309. 4 bed, two bath,
1,700 square
ft. Recess lighting, really open,
beautiful
kitchen, tile, white ceramic tile
backsplash, stainless steel
appliances, luxury vinyl plank flooring,
carpet in the master. Just an idea of
what you could get for 309. Another
community in Temple, our third one to
take a look at, Wildflower Country Club,
which is our golf course and golf club
community in Temple. The Terrace right
off of West Adams. The Hills of Westwood
is one of our gated communities, super
beautiful, super popular. It has a
community pool and park. Um, The Grove
at Lakewood Ranch off of West Adams,
Northgate off of West Adams, Mesa Ridge,
Legacy Ranch, and Hartrick's Ranch I
just showed you. So, those are some new
communities. And then I think our last
one that we'll do is let's do Wildflower
Country Club. So, these homes are a
little bit higher price per square foot
based off of location. You are in the
golf community. You can see right here
294, 304, 257 a square foot. So, price
per square foot is going to be a little
higher. As you know, this is one of my
absolute favorite luxury one of my
absolute favorite builders, our luxury
builder, her brothers. I recently did a
video in Morgan's Point showing you a
giving you a really awesome tour of a
Kurther's new construction home. The
outside of the these are absolutely
beautiful. You have a lot of trees. A
lot of part of the price per square foot
increase in here has to do with the
finishes and things that they put into
the home. So, even though you are paying
a little bit more, you get what you pay
for. Sometimes those starter homes are
fantastic, but you're able to often get
a little bit more square footage. This
one is clearly still
in under
construction. They're doing the
two-toned cabinets, really fun light
fixtures, tons of lighting. You are in a
golf course, you don't have that privacy
fencing. If you're a golfer or you love
that open feel that the golf community
offers and you want a really beautiful
builder, this is a great one for us to
take a look at. So, yeah, that's a
that's a little glimpse into what you
can buy in the Temple area. Big range
between $300,000 homes, million-dollar
homes, and those many communities I
mentioned, some of our biggest builders
in all of these areas. There's going to
be quite a bit of overlap, but we have
Dr. Horton, Kila Homes, Omega, Flint
Rock, Style Craft, some of the big like
the big production builders. You also
have builds in smaller volumes. Suri
Wright, BB Fuller, Corey Herring, White
River, Rocky Creek. Let's go ahead and
take a look at what you can find in
Belton, Texas. When we run a search of
homes available in Belton, Texas, brand
new, 62 homes populate and we sort by
price as low as
229. Most of them are going to be over
that 260 price point. A lot of them are
within
$300,000, about four in $400,000 price
point, a few in that $700,000 price
point, and a few just over a million. Of
course, if you wanted to build custom,
would I could always talk to you about
what that looks like in terms of buying
land and working with a a new home
custom builder. That process is a whole
another conversation. But today, in
terms of built-in, we're going to look
at Three Creeks, Rancho Delago, and
Honey Glenn Acres. Ranch of Delago. This
is the community that I did the
Kurther's home tour in a couple months.
Ranch of Delago is going to be up here
in Morgan's Point. Love this area. Dear
roaming your neighborhood, just minutes
from the lake. Even have some houses
that are Lake View. Not in that
community, but in Morgan's Point. We're
going to look at Honey Glenn Acres,
which is more down here. And then we're
going to look at Three Creeks. So, Three
Creeks, west side of 35. There are so
many builders in this community. Some of
the biggest ones I and one of the
reasons I like to highlight this
community is because of that variety.
It's a very established community, one
of the only communities where you're
finding a ton resale, but also new
construction homes, those smaller priced
homes. Dear Horton, Stylecraft, Tippet
is in there. You also still have
Kurther's building in there as well. I
think Omega and Kila might be done in
there. But huge variety, lots of new
homes, lots of resale homes, very
aggressive in terms of finding a new
home. You're also minutes away from
Stillhouse Lake, 20 minutes from Fort
Cavazos, an hour away from Austin, 45
minutes from Waco. Also walking trails
and a creek, a pavilion, a lot of
really, really awesome amenities in that
community. This is a Tippet home, still
under construction, but it's on a really
great size lot. 1 9 1,800 square ft² 4
bed, three bath priced at 319. It's
actually less per square foot currently
than a lot of the other builders, but
really pretty wood beams, light
fixtures. You'll probably have some
vinyl plank throughout, stainless steel
appliances, tile backsplash, and then
our highest priced new construction home
in Three Creeks is going to be this one
by Kurthers. Price per square foot is
reflected in the the things inside of
it. This one's a threecar garage, four
bed, two bath, 2100 ft², just shy of a/4
acre, vated ceilings, Hoffford ceilings
with recess lighting, wood beams, looks
like a wood burning fireplace, woodlike
ceramic tile, beautiful two-toned
cabinets. I love this these color
selections that they've been doing
lately. Their bathrooms are always
fantastic. So, in this one, you have
that center tub, just super elegant
finishes and a large yard. ninth variety
of price points. Really awesome access.
Honey Glenn Acres. This is going to be
the highest price point uh in currently,
I believe, in the Belton area. We This
is a Brandon Watley home priced at $1.5
million. 1 acre, 4 bed, 3 and 1 half
bath, just shy of 4,000 square ft. Did I
say 1 acre? Modern farmhouse. This one's
out towards academy. Which ISD is it?
So, you're still part of Belton ISD
within Belton. Two-story home. High
ceilings, open concept floor plan, looks
like concrete accent wall, probably
wallpaper, maybe Venetian plastering,
master bath, loft area with a wet
bar and a pool. So, this feels more farm
area to me. Whereas our final community,
Rancho Delago, I think Kurthers is the
only one currently building in this
community. 700 to $800,000 price point.
Um just over half an acre lot. This one
is a four bed, three bath home, just
under 2700 square ft. So Morgan's Point,
you're going to have a ton of trees
still. All those deer roaming around
right close to the lake. So very
different feel between the more farm
area of Honey Glenn Acres. Stunning
kitchen. Again, those two-tone cabinets,
barrel ceiling, electric
fireplace. This is their Reagan floor
plan, and it is ceramic tile. Backyard
is just about done here. Outdoor
fireplace, outdoor grill, and outdoor
kitchen. Always topnotch with their
kitchens and bathrooms, of course. A lot
more brown than I've been seeing in a
while. And I hope that that was helpful.
Getting a good glimpse into different
that's more of our middle price point,
but getting a glimpse. Morgan's point,
you'll generally be seeing Kurthers
being the only builder still building
out there in terms of spec homes, which
means already started, they carry the
note. You come, you pick it, you buy it,
you leave versus there are still lots of
lots for sale. Our last stop is Cedo. We
are just totally switching vibes. Within
Cedo, there's a lot of more limited but
high-end new construction homes. Some of
our newer communities out there are
going to be Sterling Meadows, Mil Creek
Meadows, The Sanctuary, Flint Ridge, and
Eagle Ranch. Okay, so if we look at all
of these homes here in Cedo, sorting by
price, lowest price at 3.44 and then our
highest priced home at $8.69. 69. Let's
go ahead and sort by subdivision and
start off in Eagle Heights. So, of
course, Kathers is building here, too.
They're building in a lot of places, but
good good uh idea to see different areas
that these various builders are building
in. So, this one's priced at 3.99,
originally $419. You can see they've had
that price drop. 4 bed, 2 and 1/2 bath,
1858 ft². So, one of the lower priced
homes in St. electric fireplace, double
tray ceilings, smaller but still great
size kitchen. Got ceramic tile, the wet
areas and kitchen, main living spaces,
some of their threecar
garages. This one's beautiful. So, this
one's an Eagle Heights. You have those
big oak trees out front really capturing
the front of the home. I know that
landscaping is going to be beautiful
with that brick and stone exterior, of
course. Oh my gosh, look at those vated
ceilings. Beautiful pendant lighting
throughout. Gorgeous accent
fireplace. Stunning, stunning, stunning
home. Tone cabinets, that honey oak and
black centered island, soaking tub,
walk-in shower, dual vanities, always
huge walk-in closets, wonderful backyard
again with that outdoor kitchen, tons of
trees, and this guy is priced at $6.99.
So, four bed, three bath, 2700 ft² home
on half an acre. And if we look on the
map, this community is just off of
I35,
Cedo, off of
2484. So if we zoom out more, you can
see you have Belton Temple, and then
Gerald continuing down 35, Georgetown,
Round Rock, and then Austin down here
somewhere. Amazing location, amazing lot
sizes, amazing home. Let's also take a
look at one more community while we're
out here. Let's look at Flint Ridge.
This is on the opposite side of 35. You
have builders like Lonar in here, King
Ranch Road. This is Duran Homes. I
always love his kitchens. Office. He
Aren't they so pretty? Really great job
on the details and selections in this
one. Chef
Dream Pop filler farmhouse sink. That's
the word I'm looking for.
Vaulted ceilings, tons of lighting,
accent
fireplace, accent walls, farmhouse, farm
door into the master bathroom. He also
loves his outdoor kitchens. I bet
there's one on here. Let's go. Yep.
Outdoor kitchen and a really great size
lot. Homes homes out here are on septic.
Generally in our area, if you get over a
half acre, you're generally on septic.
That is just our glimpse into your three
different areas, Temple, Belt, and Celo.
Very overlapping builders. I know them
well. And if you would like any more
information on builders in this area, um
if you'd like to get an idea of
inventory, incentives that are being
offered, you want me to give you a
virtual tour, and just help you out, get
you started, you know, I'm here to do
it.
um tax rates. So your generally your
lowest property taxes are going to be in
the you can find probably 1.7 to 1.9 in
Temple Beltton area. Just depending on
where you're at, you're looking at two
just over two to 2.7 uh kind of
depending on where you're at. So that
can affect your monthly payment a lot.
Of course, there are exemptions if
you're a disabled veteran, if you are
over 65 exemption, your homestead
exemptions. So, those are all things to
consider. But if you'd like more
information on any of these homes, any
of these areas, or just want to know
where to get started, you can find all
my contact information below. I would
love to speak with you. Until next time,
I'm Andrea Dudik, realtor and associate
broker with Vist Real Estate.